<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<course_type	xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
				xsi:no="http://34.213.198.190/COMP466TMA2/part2/xml"
				xsi:schemaLocation="http://34.213.198.190/COMP466TMA2/part2/xml/course_type.xsd">
	<name>HTML and CSS</name>
	<code>STU100</code>
	<instructors>
		<instructor>
			<instructor_id>3</instructor_id>
			<firstname>Brad</firstname>
			<lastname>Edwards</lastname>
		</instructor>
	</instructors>
	<summary>
		<paragraph>
			<text>This course teaches the basics of HTML5 and CSS3.</text>
		</paragraph>
	</summary>
	<objectives>
		<objective>Understand the origins of the Internet.</objective>
		<objective>Understand the basics of technologies used to access the Internet.</objective>
	</objectives>
	<introduction>
		<paragraph>
			<text>The Internet is a defining technology of the late 1900's and early 2000's. It has changed the way people communicate, buy, entertain themselves and work. This vast network is arguably among the most vital pieces of infrastructure of our modern age.</text>
		</paragraph>
	</introduction>
	<sections>
		<section>
			<order>1</order>
			<title>The Web</title>
			<content>
				<paragraph>
					<text>The Internet is a global network of computers providing access to an enormous range of digital resources. The Internet evolved from ARPANET, an American military research from the 1960's. Internet protocols require the transmission of data between computers to be in chunks called packets. Packets have standardized formats that allow them to be routed between routers, switches and servers to their destinations. Some of the most important protocols used in the Internet are the Transmission Control Protocol and Internet protocols, referred to collectively as TCP/IP.</text>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph>
					<text>Multiple technologies are used together to create the web sites we access daily. HTML5, CSS and JavaScript are among the most important.</text>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph>
					<text>Most users access web sites using web browsers, applications which are responsible for fetching and rendering web pages from servers. While there are no standards for web browsers, browsers still provide a means for web pages to be viewed across many different platforms.</text>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph>
					<text>Web applications are multi-tiered and often feature a client, web server and a database server. In this three-tiered architecture, the database is bottom tier and maintains application data. The middle-tier sits between the top-tier (client tier) and the bottom tier and implements the application and presentation logic. The top-tier interprets data from the middle-tier and presents it to the user.</text>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph>
					<text>Many web servers exist to receive and respond to client requests. Server applications can be found to operate on any operating system. The most popular web server is Apache HTTP Server, most often run on a Linux operating system. Microsoft has developed the Internet Information Services (IIS) server for its own operating system.</text>
				</paragraph>
			</content>
		</section>
		<section>
			<order>2</order>
			<title>HTML</title>
			<content>
				<subsection>
					<order>1</order>
					<level>2</level>
					<title>Overview</title>
					<content>
						<paragraph>
							<text>In 1991, Tim Berners-Lee developed HyperText Markup Language (HTML), a markup language for creating hyperlinked text documents. He also created the Hypertext Transfer Protocol (HTTP) to control the transmission of HTML documents between computers. HTTP has become the most dominant protocol on the Internet at its network layer. A version of HTTP called Hypertext Transfer Protocol Secure (HTTPS) combines HTTP with Secure Sockets Layer (SSL) or Transport Layer Security (TLS) to provide encrypted communications.</text>
						</paragraph>
						<paragraph>
							<text>HTML5 is a markup language used to create the content and structure of documents, usually accessed online using web browsers. It is the successor to HTML and incorporates a raft of new features for rendering complex documents.</text>
						</paragraph>
						<paragraph>
							<text>HTML documents consist of text content with annotations that web browsers interpret in order to structure the content and refer to other resources such as other documents, images, videos and more. The annotations that reference other resouces are called hyperlinks, hence the name of the markup language.</text>
						</paragraph>
						<paragraph>
							<text>Resources are located over the Internet using Uniform Resource Identifiers. These are human-readable names that indicate which server to access, and the location of the requested resource on the server. These requests are generally sent using the HTTP protocol.</text>
						</paragraph>
						<paragraph>
							<text>HTTP protocol specifies message formats to allow servers and clients to interpret message. HTTP methods tell servers what a client is trying to do. The GET message is for requesting a resource while POST is used for sending information to the server.</text>
						</paragraph>
					</content>
				</subsection>
				<subsection>
					<order>2</order>
					<level>2</level>
					<title>HTML5</title>
					<content>
						<paragraph>
							<text>HTML files are saved with .html or .htm extensions. Some operating systems do not allow four letter file extensions, hence the need for .htm extension. HTML5 annotations consist of names and properties enclosed in angle brackets called tags. For example, this is a paragraph tag:</text>
						</paragraph>
						<paragraph>
							<indent />
							<text>&lt;p&gt;Paragraph text&lt;/p&gt;.</text>
						</paragraph>
						<paragraph>
							<text>Properly formed HTML files start with &lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt; tag, which identifies the document as an HTML file. The base tags of an HTML file, called the root, are the &lt;html&gt; tag. The basic structure of an HTML document is shown below.
							</text>
						</paragraph>
						<paragraph>
							<text>&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;</text><break />
							<indent /><text>&lt;html&gt;</text><break />
							<indent /><indent /><text>&lt;head&gt;</text><break />
							<indent /><indent /><indent /><text>&lt;meta charset = 'utf-8'&gt;</text><break />
							<text>&lt;title&gt;Welcome&lt;/title&gt;</text><break /> 
							<indent /><indent /><indent /><text>&lt;link rel='stylesheet' src='styles.css'&gt;</text><break />
							<indent /><indent /><text>&lt;/head&gt;</text><break />
							<indent /><indent /><text>&lt;body&gt;</text><break />
							<indent /><indent /><indent /><text>&lt;p&gt;This is some HTML5&lt;/p&gt;</text><break />
							<indent /><indent /><text>&lt;/body&gt;</text><break />
							<text>&lt;/html&gt;</text>
						</paragraph>
						<paragraph>
							<text>The &lt;html&gt; is the root of the document and encompasses all HTML elements in the document.These tags are needed as the HTML could be embedded within elements of another document type such as XML.</text>
						</paragraph>
						<subsection>
							<order>1</order>
							<level>3</level>
							<title>&lt;head&gt;</title>
							<paragraph>
								<text>The &lt;head&gt; tag may contain information about the HTML document, such as the character set, specified by the &lt;meta&gt; tag and links to resources such as CSS sheets and JavaScript scripts. Resources to be included in the document are put in &lt;link&gt; tags. &lt;link&gt; tags, as with many other HTML elements, may have attributes. In the case of the &lt;link&gt; tag, 'rel' declares the relationship between the linked resource and the HTML document. In the case above the rel attribute indicates the linked resource is a stylesheet. The 'type' attribute declares the type of the linked resource and the 'href' attribute gives the location of the resouce to link. The &lt;title&gt; tag is often displayed by browsers as the title of the tab in which the document is displayed.</text>
							</paragraph>			
						</subsection>
						<subsection>
							<order>2</order>
							<level>3</level>
							<title>&lt;body&gt;</title>
							<paragraph>
								<text>The &lt;body&gt; contains the content of the document. There are many tags that can be contained within the &lt;body&gt; tags. The paragraph element, &lt;p&gt;, groups text into a paragraph. Several other elements can be used to declare various levels of headers. Header elements are &lt;h1&gt;, &lt;h2&gt;, &lt;h3&gt;, etc. Images can be included using &lt;img&gt; tags with a 'src' to provide its location. List elements are also available, both ordered (&lt;ol&gt;) and unordered (&lt;ul&gt;). List elements included within the parent tags using the &lt;li&gt; tags.</text>
							</paragraph>
						</subsection>
						<subsection>
							<order>3</order>
							<level>3</level>
							<title>Tables</title>
							<content>
								<paragraph>
									<text>&lt;table&gt;</text><break />
									<indent /><text>&lt;thead&gt;</text><break />
									<indent /><indent /><text>&lt;tr&gt;</text><break />
									<indent /><indent /><indent /><text>&lt;th&gt;Header 1&lt;/th&gt;</text><break />
									<indent /><indent /><indent /><text>&lt;th&gt;Header 2&lt;/th&gt;</text><break />
									<indent /><indent /><text>&lt;/tr&gt;</text><break />
									<indent /><text>&lt;/thead&gt;</text><break />
									<indent /><text>&lt;/tbody&gt;</text><break />
									<indent /><indent /><text>&lt;tr&gt;</text><break />
									<indent /><indent /><indent /><text>&lt;td&gt;Cell Text&lt;/td&gt;</text><break />
									<indent /><indent /><indent /><text>&lt;td&gt;Cell Text&lt;/td&gt;</text><break />
									<indent /><indent /><text>&lt;/tr&gt;</text><break />
									<indent /><text>&lt;/tbody&gt;</text><break />
									<indent /><text>&lt;/tfoot&gt;</text><break />
									<indent /><indent /><text>&lt;tr&gt;</text><break />
									<indent /><indent /><indent /><text>&lt;th&gt;Footer 1&lt;/th&gt;</text><break />
									<indent /><indent /><indent /><text>&lt;th&gt;Footer 2&lt;/th&gt;</text><break />
									<indent /><indent /><text>&lt;/tr&gt;</text><break />
									<indent /><text>&lt;/tfoot&gt;</text><break />
									<text>&lt;/table&gt;</text>
								</paragraph>
								<paragraph>
									<text>Tables can be created using HTML using the elements in the examle above. The header, body and footer elements are self-explanatory. The table row tags, &lt;tr&gt;, enclose data for a single row. The &lt;th&gt; enclose header or footer cell data for each row, and the &lt;td&gt; enclose data for rows within the table body.</text>
								</paragraph>
							</content>
						</subsection>
						<subsection>
							<order>4</order>
							<level>3</level>
							<title>Links</title>
							<content>
								<paragraph>
									<text>Links are another important element. A link element such as &lt;a href='www.someaddress.com'&gt;Click here &lt;/a&gt; would create a hyperlink to the address listed in the href attribute.</text>
							</content>
						</subsection>
						<subsection>
							<order>5</order>
							<level>3</level>
							<title>Forms</title>
							<content>
								<paragraph>
									<text>HTML forms are a means to allow users to submit information to a web server in a moderately structured way. Forms can include a a number of different kinds of input elements:</text><break />
									<indent /><list>
										<ordered>false</ordered>
										<list_items>
											<list_item>color</list_item>
											<list_item>date</list_item>
											<list_item>datetime</list_item>
											<list_item>datetime-local</list_item>
											<list_item>email</list_item>
											<list_item>number</list_item>
											<list_item>range</list_item>
											<list_item>search</list_item>
											<list_item>tel</list_item>
											<list_item>time</list_item>
											<list_item>url</list_item>
											<list_item>week</list_item>
										</list_items>
									</list>
								</paragraph>
								<paragraph>
									<text>Input tags within a form can be set to any of these types to submit data. Forms take the following general shape:</text><break />
									<indent /><text>&lt;form method='post' action = 'http://www.aserver.com'&gt;</text><break />
									<indent /><indent /><text>&lt;label&gt;Color&lt;/label&gt;</text><break />
									<indent /><indent /><text>&lt;input type='color' autofocus/&gt;</text><break />
									<indent /><text>&lt;/form&gt;</text><break />
								</paragraph>
								<paragraph>
									<text>The method attribute in this example declares the input will use the HTTP POST method in its message to the server. The action attribute indicates the server to target with the POST message.</text>
								</paragraph>
							</content>
						</subsection>
					</content>
				</subsection>
			</content>
		</section>
		<section>
			<order>3</order>
			<title>Cascading Style Sheets</title>
			<content>
				<paragraph>
					<text>Cascading style sheets (CSS) are documents used to style HTML/5 documents. Using CSS allows developers to declare the structure and content of web pages in HTML and the presentation of web pages in separate CSS documents. CSS can be applied to multiple web pages in a site, each page simply needs to import the stylesheet using a link element.</text>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph>
					<text>Styles can be declared within HTML documents using the style attribute on the different tags. Unfortunately, this requires declaring the necessary styles separately in every tag in every document in a web site. External stylesheets referenced in the way already shown allow styles to be declared once and applied across the website.</text>text>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph>
					<text>CSS stylesheets consist of a series of statements. Each statement starts with one selector or several in a comma-separated list, which declare which HTML elements the style will target. After the selectors, properties and their values are put between curly braces in a semi-colon separated list. The properties available for each element can vary.</text>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph>
					<text>Each element in a web page can be conceptualized as existing within a box on the screen. All of the element's contents, including any child elements, are contained within the box. The margin property can be used to enforce a distance between the target element's border and other outside elements specified in pixels, percentages of the available space to the element or em's, which are linked to the size of individual characters in the current font. The padding property is very similar, however it sets the distance between the border of an element and its contents. The following is an example of a stylesheet entry:</text><break />
					<indent /><text>p {</text><break />
					<indent /><indent /><text>width: 10px;</text><break />
					<indent /><indent /><text>height: 10px;</text><break />
					<indent /><indent /><text>margin: 10px, 15px, 10px, 15px;</text><break />
					<indent /><text>}</text>
				</paragraph>
				<paragraph>
					<text>The selector targets paragraph tags and the style properties set the height, width and margin properties of all paragraph elements in any document that references a stylesheet with that entry. There are too many properties to list here and CSS is a complicated technology with many corner cases. However, two important HTML element attributes help with targetting CSS styles. Each HTML element can have an id and class attribute set. The value of an id element must be unique within the context of a given HTML document. Multiple elements can have the same class value. In a CSS file, id and class values can be used in style selectors to target the relevant elements. An id value of 'uniqueElement' would be entered as '#uniqueElement' in a CSS selector. A class value of 'oneOfManyElements' would be entered as '.oneOfManyElements'. Id or class selectors can be combined with element selectors to target elements that are child elements of an element with a given id or class value. For instance, '#uniqueElement p' would target paragraph elements which are children of an element with an id of 'uniqueElement'.</text>
				</paragraph>
			</content>
		</section>
	</sections>
	<assignments>
	</assignments>
	<quizzes>
		<quiz>
			<order>1</order>
			<title>HTML and CSS Quiz</title>
			<weight>100</weight>
			<questions>
				<question>
					<order>1</order>
					<text>HTML5 is a:</text>
					<options>
						<option>
							<order>1</order>
							<text>Natural Language</text>
						</option>
						<option>
							<order>2</order>
							<text>Programming Language</text>
						</option>
						<option>
							<order>3</order>
							<text>Markup Language</text>
						</option>
						<option>
							<order>4</order>
							<text>Asynchronous Language</text>
						</option>
					</options>
					<answer>3</answer>
				</question>
				<question>
					<order>2</order>
					<text>HTML documents have which file extensions:</text>
					<options>
						<option>
							<order>1</order>
							<text>.htm</text>
						</option>
						<option>
							<order>2</order>
							<text>.html</text>
						</option>
						<option>
							<order>3</order>
							<text>.h</text>
						</option>
						<option>
							<order>4</order>
							<text>.html or .htm</text>
						</option>
					</options>
					<answer>4</answer>
				</question>
				<question>
					<order>3</order>
					<text>Which of the following is not an input type for an HTML form?</text>
					<options>
						<option>
							<order>1</order>
							<text>number</text>
						</option>
						<option>
							<order>2</order>
							<text>time</text>
						</option>
						<option>
							<order>3</order>
							<text>email</text>
						</option>
						<option>
							<order>4</order>
							<text>week</text>
						</option>
					</options>
					<answer>2</answer>
				</question>
				<question>
					<order>4</order>
					<text>CSS stands for:</text>
					<options>
						<option>
							<order>1</order>
							<text>Cascading Style Sheets</text>
						</option>
						<option>
							<order>2</order>
							<text>Controlled Style Sheets</text>
						</option>
						<option>
							<order>3</order>
							<text>Cascading Style System</text>
						</option>
						<option>
							<order>4</order>
							<text>Controlled Services Subsystem</text>
						</option>
					</options>
					<answer>1</answer>
				</question>
			</questions>
		</quiz>
	</quizzes>
</course_type>